Preliminary Guide to the Elizabeth A. McMahan Papers, 1926-2010 and undated RL.00880
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Elizabeth A. McMahan papers
1926-2010 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
McMahan, Elizabeth A.
RL.00880
16.4 Linear Feet
9105 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Elizabeth A. McMahan Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2003-2011.
Biographical Note
Entomologist (termite biology), psychologist, cartoonist, writer of children's books, and ocean traveler. McMahan is credited with 59 publications, many under the name E. A. McMahan, including 11 children's books.
Chronology
1924 Born, Davie County, N.C.
1946 A.B., Duke University, Major in Psychology
1948 M.A. in Psychology, Duke University
1943-1954 Research Assistant, Parapsychology Laboratory, Duke University. Close friend of Rhine family.
1960 Ph.D, Entomology, University of Hawaii
1960-1961 Post-doctoral work, Zoology, University of Chicago
1961-1987 Professor, Department of Biology, UNC-Chapel Hill. Received outstanding teaching award in 1970.
1987-1988 Peace Corps, College of Agriculture, Port Antonio, Jamaica
1989 Received North Carolina Entomological Society's Award of Excellence for contributions to entomology.
1989-2009 Retired to Carolina Meadows, a retirement community in Chapel Hill, N.C.
2009 Died, Chapel Hill, N.C.
Collection Overview
The collection contains primarily correspondence and greeting cards, including correspondence with John Craig Wheeler (considered the father of black holes) on parapsychology and its intersection with theoretical physics. Also includes news clippings and scrapbooks documenting McMahan's life; illustrations she made describing her travels aboard Pacific-traveling cargo ships; several of her self-published children's books; and compilations of her cartoons from The Meadowlark, a newsletter published by Carolina Meadows, a retirement community in Chapel Hill, N.C. Acquired as part of the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture.
Subsequent additions include materials relating to McMahan's termite research; book illustrations; her early life, including school materials and World War II ephemera; and personal correspondence with friends and relatives. Also includes a memorial tribute to her.
Related Material
Parapsychology Laboratory Records, 1893-1984
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Louisa E. Rhine Papers, 1890-1983
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Cartoons; Clippings (information artifacts); Duke University -- Alumni and alumnae; Entomologists -- North Carolina; Scrapbooks; Parapsychology and science; Self-publishing -- United States; Termites; Psychometry (Parapsychology); Caricatures and cartoons; Cargo ships -- Passenger traffic; Children's literature; Books and reading; Ocean travel; Pacific Ocean -- Description and travel; McMahan, Elizabeth A. -- Travel; McMahan, Elizabeth A.; Rhine, J. B. (Joseph Banks), 1895-1980; Wheeler, J. Craig; McMahan, Elizabeth A.
- Accession 2003-0128
  - Contents of Box 1: (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1957-1980 (Box 1)
    - Clippings, 1980-2002 (Box 1)
  - Contents of Box 2: (Box 2)
    - Rhine Correspondence, 1946-1975 (Box 2)
      Scope and Contents note
      Includes letters and hand-made birthday cards to J.B. Rhine. Also contains letters to family from Costa Rica and Puerto Rico.
    - Big Book of Animal Behavior (Box 2)
    - Loose material removed from scrapbook in box 4, 1960-1978 (Box 2)
      Includes original artwork, newspaper, and magazine clippings.
    - Videotape: Wall Cartoons (Vic and Jim Smith Video) (Box 2)
  - Contents of Box 3: (Box 3)
    - Correspondence with John Wheeler, 1986 (Box 3)
    - Writings
      - Life at Carolina Meadows series (Box 3)
      - Children's books (Box 3)
      - The Meadowlark newsletter (Box 3)
    - Curriculum vitae (Box 3)
    - Artwork, cartoon illustrations (Box 3)
    - Clippings and greeting cards, [1964-2001] (Box 3)
  - Contents of Box 4: (Box 4)
    - Scrapbook, 1941-1962 (Box 4)
      Includes clippings, correspondence and photographs.
- Accession (2003-0270), 1926-2008, 3 boxes
  Addition consists of McMahan's artwork, correspondence (including with friend and colleague Howard T. Odum), photographs, journals, diplomas, and other ephemera.
- Accession (2004-0334), 1972-2004, 1 Box, 1 Oversize Folder
  Addition comprises correspondence, field notes, journals, and sketch books related to McMahan's termite research. Also includes newsletters, photographs, certificates, and awards.
- Accession (2006-0012), 1940-2006, 8 boxes
  Addition comprises primarily original illustrations by McMahan. Also includes correspondence, children's stories, cartoons, a sketchbook, postcards, poetry, lecture notes, travel journals, clippings and one VHS tape containing an interview with McMahan held in 2004.
- Accession (2006-0034), 1967-2005, 4 boxes
  Addition comprises primarily correspondence written by McMahan to Burke Smith; 6 photographs; clippings; and sketches of cartoons by the donor.
- Accession (2007-0016), 1999-2006, 2 boxes
  - Miscellaneous emails and clippings (Box 1)
  - Email correspondence, 1999-2003 (Box 1)
  - Email correspondence, 2003-2005 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence with sister, Mary Lee Doyle, 2006 (Box 2)
- Accession (2007-0076), 1934-2006, 4 boxes
  - Correspondence (Box 1)
  - Clippings (Box 1)
  - Sketches (Box 1)
  - Journal (Box 2)
  - Ephemera from a European trip, 1950s (Box 2)
  - Correspondence 1950 (Box 2)
  - Postcards (Box 2)
  - War ration books, 1942 (Box 2)
  - Student handbook, 1960-1961 (Box 2)
  - Senior diary, 1935 (Box 2)
  - Record of payments for work in Parapsychology lab, 1943-1945 (Box 2)
  - Research notebook, 1975 (Box 2)
  - Autograph book, 1936-1939 (Box 2)
  - School treasures book, 1934 (Box 2)
  - Wood engraving (Box 2)
  - Name cards (Box 2)
  - Autograph book (Box 2)
  - Postcards (Box 2)
  - Diary, 1936 (Box 2)
  - Autographed wooden spoons, 1940 (Box 2)
  - Address book (Box 2)
  - Correspondence (Box 3)
  - Drawings for Camie book (Box 3)
  - Plaque from the Entomological Society for support, 1993 (Box 3)
  - Clippings (Box 3)
  - Materials from elementary school (Box 3)
  - Scrapbook (Box 4)
  - Clippings (Box 4)
  - Sketches for Camie (Box 4)
- Accession (2007-0203), 1950-2007, 1 boxes
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1980s-2007 (4 folders) (Box 1)
  - Hoyle correspondence, 2007 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence and photographs, 1950s (Box 1)
  - Rhine Center correspondence (Box 1)
  - Carolina Meadows material (Box 1)
  - Public Health Service Research Fellowship Application, 1959 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous photographs (Box 1)
- Accession (2008-0264), 2007-2008, 1 boxes
  - Carolina Meadows publications (Box 1)
  - Email correspondence, 2007-2008 (5 folders) (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous email correspondence, 2008 (3 folders) (Box 1)
- Accessions (2009-0203 and 2009-0206), 1 box
  Addition (2009-0203) (100 items; 0.4 lin. ft.; dated 1946-1987) includes a Thematic Apperception Test, Duke parapsychology lab communications, color slides of Duke's campus (1957), UNC Department of Zoology correspondence, materials on Donald Costello and Burke Smith, and miscellaneous materials from McMahan's retirement in 1987. Addition (2009-0206) (1 item; 0.2 lin. ft.; dated 1950s-1960s) consists of a photo album with unlabelled photographs of the J.B. Rhine family and the Duke parapsychology laboratory.
  - 16 color slides from Duke's West Campus, 1957 (Box 1)
  - 8 color slides of the K.M. Wilbur family, including children Gretchen and Louise; Dr. J.R. Bailey; Dr. Horn and Kathy, 1957 (Box 1)
  - Thematic Apperception Test, 1946 (Box 1)
    Includes cards, manuals, and interpretation guide.
  - Duke materials (Box 1)
    Includes Department of Zoology correspondence, 1960s, and Nixon Library correspondence, 1981.
  - Donald Costello, 1970s (Box 1)
  - Burke Smith correspondence, 1984-1986 (Box 1)
  - Parapscyhology (Box 1)
  - Retirement, 1987 (Box 1)
  - Voices: the Literary Magazine of Carolina Meadows, Spring 2009 (Box 1)
  - Photo album (Box 1)
    Includes unlabelled photographs of J.B. Rhine, his family, and the Duke Parapscyhology Laboratory, 1950s-1960s.
- Accession (2009-0222), 2 boxes
  Addition (2009-0222) (700 items; 1.2 lin. ft.) includes subject files, correspondence, and other materials from McMahan's retirement. Subjects include Jamaica, freighter travel, UNC's Zoology Department, etc. Box 2 of this material is housed with Acc. 2010-0132.
  - Society of Woman Geographers (Box 1)
  - Australia (Box 1)
  - Professional correspondence, 2002 (Box 1)
  - General mail and email, 2002 (Box 1)
  - References (Box 1)
  - India (Box 1)
  - Lin Frye: CMSW UNC/Vance Co., July 1994 (Box 1)
  - Zukeran (Box 1)
  - Peace Corps (Jamaica), 1987-1988 (Box 1)
  - Jamaica, 1991 (Box 1)
  - Freighter travel (talks) (Box 1)
  - Arm-chair travel (freightering), 2002 (Box 1)
  - La Selva (and LTER), 1985-1986 (Box 1)
  - Talks (extras) (Box 1)
  - Sigma Xi (Box 1)
  - Unlabelled folder (miscellaneous) (Box 1)
  - Rowland, 2002 (Box 1)
  - Greenes (Box 1)
  - Capt. Chris Blake and Capt. Cook (Box 1)
  - NC State (Box 1)
  - Christy Lehrer (Nalepa) (Box 1)
  - Duke Library (Bingham Center) (Box 1)
  - UNC Zoology (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1986 (Box 2)
  - JB Rhine (Box 2)
  - Parapsychology Abstracts International, 1986 (Box 2)
  - ESP tests, 1940s (Box 2)
  - Printouts of 2 photos of JB Rhine and the parapsychology lab, 1970s (Box 2)
- Accession (2010-0132), 1 folder
  Addition (2010-0132) (29 items; 0.1 lin. ft.; dated 1985-2009 and undated) contains flyers and email from the UNC biology dept. and library; McMahan's obituaries and memorial program; two articles she published on the Assassin bug;, newspaper clippings on her work; and copies of her cartoon works, including two of her children's books.
  - Accession (2010-0132) (Box 2)
- Accession (2011-0124), 1 folder
  Addition (2011-0124) (2 items, 0.1 lin. ft.; dated 2010) comprises a journal copy of SOCIOBIOLOGY (2010 Vol. 56, no. 1) containing a memorial tribute to McMahan, along with a reprint of the piece.
  - Accession (2011-0124) (Box 2)